John Curtis and Mary Snell Smith Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
John Curtis and Mary Snell Smith Papers
1837-1873
1853-1869
RG 207
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(7 boxes)
John Curtis Smith and Mary Snell Steele Smith were Congregational missionaries from New England who served in Ceylon (now Sri Lanka), which was then part of the India Mission of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. This collection provides intensive documentation for the lives of missionary families especially "missionary children" and their extended families in the 1850s through the early 1870s. Of particular value in this collection is the large number of letters written by the Smith children themselves. The six children in the Smith family were all born in Ceylon and spent at least half of their childhoods there before being sent or taken to live in the United States, where they resided with relatives and friends in New England.
Smith, John Curtis
Smith, Mary Snell Steele
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Philip C. Smith, grandson of Henry Hill Smith, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
John Curtis Smith and Mary Snell Steele Smith were Congregational missionaries from New England who served at posts in Ceylon, then part of the India Mission of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, in the mid-nineteenth century. Mary Snell (21 September 1814--14 May 1873) was born in Plainfield, Massachusetts. A teacher, she embarked for India in November, 1836 with her husband, Dr. John Steele, a physician-missionary. John Curtis Smith (24 September 1812—21 March 1884) was born and raised in Williamstown, Vermont and was a graduate of Middlebury College (1838) and Andover Seminary (1841). After graduation, he married in1841 and embarked for Ceylon on 14 October 1841 with his wife, who was a teacher, Eunice Taft Morse Smith (15 April 1815-9 May 1842). Soon after they arrived in India, Eunice Morse Smith died of consumption. Dr. John Steele died in October 1842, after an illness.
John Curtis Smith and Mary Snell Steele were married in Ceylon on 13 October 1843. In the years following their marriage, Mary Snell Smith gave birth to six children, all were born in Ceylon: Thomas Snell Smith (24 January 1845—16 December 1900); Eunice Morse Smith (11 February 1846—August 1872), named for Smith's first wife; Laura Parkhurst Smith (31 December 1847--3 June 1872), William Halleck Smith (10 August 1850--24 July 1924), Henry Hill Smith (6 December 1851—19 January 1934) and Mary Elizabeth Smith (28 March 1853—December, 1929). Eight-year-old Thomas Snell Smith and his sister, seven-year-old Eunice Morse Smith sailed from Madras, India in December 1853 in the company of a missionary couple, Susan Tolman Mills and Cyrus T. Mills. After spending several weeks in Cape Town, South Africa, the two children, with their escorts, arrived at Boston in mid-May 1854; arrangements had been made for them to live with relatives in Amherst, Massachusetts.
After sojourns in Ceylon of fourteen and twenty years respectively, John Curtis Smith and Mary Snell Steele Smith journeyed to the United States via London, leaving Ceylon in late 1856 and arriving in Boston in May, 1857, with their four younger children—Laura, William, Henry, and Mary. After John and Mary Smith traveled around New England to visit their two older children, and then to see relatives, both in New England and in Illinois and Minnesota, the family seems to have united briefly in Central Village (MA or CT), while arrangements were made to leave Laura, William, Henry, and their oldest children Thomas and Eunice behind in the United States. John Curtis Smith and Mary Snell Smith, with their youngest child, Mary, returned to Ceylon in 1860. Mary was sent to the United States in 1865, while her parents remained in Ceylon.
For more detailed biographical accounts of the Smith parents and children, especially during the time period covered in this collection (1850s and 1860s), see biographical sketches written by Elizabeth C. Stevens in Series IV, Box 7.
Scope and Contents
The John Curtis Smith and Mary Snell Steele Smith Family Papers consist primarily of seven letterbooks (originally eight letterbooks; one letterbook which was in poor condition was dismantled and the letters put in folders), three journals, one memorandum book, and a number of unbound letters, now in folders, which may have been intended for several more letterbooks. Counting the letters in the letterbooks as individual items, the collection consists of a total of just over 2,000 items. Other items beside letters and journals include small bits of fabric (samples from the girls' dresses), a few programs from various school ceremonies, essays written by the children, a parrot feather, an ordination sermon, certificates for a children's fund-raising project, a copy of the printed sermon preached at John Curtis Smith's funeral service, a few family genealogical papers, and photographs of John Curtis and Mary Snell Smith and their children. However, the collection is almost exclusively letters; most of them are from the 1840s, 1850s and 1860s.
The vast majority of the correspondence in this collection concerns the offspring of John Curtis Smith and Mary Snell Steele Smith. The children were sent or brought to the United States to live with relatives. There are scores of letters from the families with whom the children stayed, as well as letters from the Smith children in the United States to their parents in Ceylon, and letters from the children to each other in the United States and Ceylon. For instance, one letterbook consists of letters that her siblings sent to Mary E. Smith, the youngest child, who lived alone with her parents in Udupitty, Ceylon, from 1861-1865, while her five older siblings were residing in the United States. Some letters from John Curtis Smith and Mary Snell Smith to their children survive in the collection, the majority of letters are ones sent out to John and Mary Smith in Ceylon by their children, their children's caregivers and other relatives during their long separation from each other. Other items in the collection include a "memorandum book," (a daily journal kept by Smith with detailed accounts of his work in Ceylon during 1861-65), notebooks that Smith wrote detailing his two voyages out to Ceylon (1841-42, 1860-61), an account of Mary E. Smith's voyage to the United States from Ceylon when she was twelve years old, and a letterbook (which has been dismantled; the contents are now in folders) with letters to John Curtis Smith from his siblings, four of whom were living in the United States and one of whom, Asa B. Smith, served for a time as a missionary to Native Americans in the American West and in Hawaii.
This collection provides intensive documentation for the lives of missionary families, especially "missionary children," and their extended families in the 1850s and especially the 1860s and early 1870s. By traveling to distant lands to convert the "heathen" to Christianity, missionaries were considered by those in America to have made the ultimate sacrifice of health and material comfort. In deciding to send their children back to the United States, thousands of miles away from their foreign households, missionaries made additional sacrifice. Missionary mothers, like Mary Smith, gave up their children so they could continue their missionary work abroad. In nineteenth century culture, indeed, even today, the extended separation of a mother from her children is considered to be a most painful experience. To have "given up" six of her children by sending them thousands of miles away from her for years at a time, Mary Snell Smith placed her calling as a missionary above the temporal earthly maternal ties that were so celebrated by her culture.
Pious relatives in New England also made a sacrifice on behalf of faith. "I never thought I would see you again in this world," wrote Mary Snell Smith's father to her of her departure from Boston in 1836; she did not return to the United States until more than twenty years later. The piety of those left behind who believed fervently in the "mission" of their loved ones in far off lands is nowhere more evident than in their willingness to take in the "orphaned missionary children" who were sent back to the States to be educated. Some sheltering relatives had already raised families and most were hard-working farmers; some had never married and had little experience with child-rearing, or had several children and grand-children of their own to care for. Many letters began with apologies for not writing sooner or more often, and a laundry list of the chores and illnesses and difficulties that had prevented keeping up the correspondence. These were not affluent families; expense was often an issue. Hard-working farm families accepted the Smith children into their households, where the children were educated. Smith boys helped with farm chores and the Smith girls learned the household arts. In several cases, the labor of the children was considered payment for their "board" while living with aunts, uncles and cousins. The relatives' letters to the Smiths in Ceylon are not only filled with updates on the children, "home news" and a chronicle of the health, births and deaths in their own and neighboring families, news of their local churches and clergy, but profound expressions of their own Christian faith, in the value of the Smiths' missionary work and the awesome responsibility of raising the missionaries' children.
A particular value in this collection is the great number of letters written by the Smith children themselves. There may be few collections of any kind that hold so many letters written by child siblings in mid-nineteenth century America. The six children in the Smith family were all born in Ceylon (now Sri Lanka) and spent at least half of their childhoods there before being sent or taken to live in the United States. The "culture shock" was both wonderful for them (snow!!!) and difficult (bland Yankee farm cooking, separation from parents and moving from household to household). Even though all five Smith children lived in New England, months or years would pass when they would not see one other, and they were only all five together in one place, perhaps three or four times in the years that their parents were away. The children felt varying degrees of attachment to their sheltering relatives, and accepted that they had little choice in the matter. In their letters back to Ceylon, the children expressed compliance with their parents' wishes to have them live apart from them, there was a great deal of sadness and sense of loss which the children openly explained and some rebellion. When Thomas Snell Smith, the oldest sibling reached his mid-teens he began to assume a paternal role in overseeing the education and well-being of his younger siblings in the United States, and in assuring that a regular stream of letters from the siblings reached their parents in Ceylon. The letters created a "virtual household" for the children and their parents during the time of separation.
Aside from the value of these letters to those studying missionary culture, the documents in this collection provide an important window into nineteenth century American culture in general. The letters, written by relatives, many of whom were from pious New England farm families, detail daily life in New England towns and on the farms—money problems, the Civil War, deaths, births, harvesting, cooking, celebrating holidays, church life are all documented here. The Smiths' relatives, while literate, clearly found letter-writing a chore, and were the sorts of people who wouldn't have ordinarily left such a complete documentation of their lives.. A sister of John Curtis Smith, Laura Smith Parkhurst, married and moved to a remote part of Illinois in the 1840's. Her comprehensive letters detail living in a log cabin in isolation from neighbors, and her struggle to bear a living child would be of interest to women's history scholars and students of the American West. Any student of nineteenth century American children would find these letters of value for the accounts of the daily activities of the Smith children and especially the various ways they were educated—in small village schools that met for three-month terms, in their relatives' homes, with local clergy, and in boarding schools and colleges. There are particularly rich and detailed accounts of Thomas's four years at Amherst College in the mid-1860's, and the months spent at Mt. Holyoke Female Seminary by Eunice and Laura. For those studying children and evangelical religion in the nineteenth century, these letters provide documentation of the spiritual struggles of children and young adults. The diagnoses and treatment of Eunice's and Laura's fatal illnesses would be of interest to scholars in the history of medicine and to those investigating nineteenth century women's health, or tuberculosis.
This description is excerpted from a more detailed essay about the collection prepared by Elizabeth C. Stevens, which is available in Series IV, Box 7.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1837-1873
II. Letterbooks, 1853-1868
III. Journals, 1841-1865
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1841-1866
Children of missionaries; Missions -- Sri Lanka; New England -- History; Missionaries; Smith, Asa Bowen, 1809-1886; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions -- China; Amherst College; Mount Holyoke College
- Correspondence, 1837-1873; Series I
  - Family Correspondence
    - Mary Snell Smith journal letters
      Scope and Contents
      Letters written by Mary Snell Smith to her children on a regular basis throughout the 1860s and into the 1870s until her return to the United States in 1872, mainly from the mission station at Udupitty. Each letter was written over a period of days and was intended to be seen by all the Smith children who were living in the United States. The journal letters describe MSS's daily activities and thoughts, unusual weather, events, and interesting anecdotes, as well as reports of MSS's and JCS's health, and news of other missions and missionary families.The journal letters from 1861-1865 also contain news of youngest sibling Mary E. Smith, who was in Ceylon with her parents (Mary left Ceylon in 1865 to live in the United States). In the letters, MSS provides general comments on everything from political happenings in the States (e.g., the Civil War, elections), her children's activities, and religious exhortations. The Smith children, living in the Unites States, had a system for passing their mother's journal letters among one another. Before sending a journal letter on to another sibling, a Smith child would usually initial the front page of the letter in the upper left hand corner.
      - Journal letters, 1861 Feb 14-Jul 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Journal letters, 1861 Jul 15-Nov 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Journal letters, 1862 Jan 11-Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Journal letters, 1862 May 17- Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Journal letters, 1862 Oct 29- 1863 Feb 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Journal letters, 1863 Mar 28- Jul 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Journal letters, 1863 Aug 29- Dec 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Journal letters, 1864 Jan 1- May 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Journal letters, 1864 Jun 3- Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Journal letters, 1865 Jan 21- Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Journal letters, 1865 Aug 26- 1866 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Journal letters, 1866 May 16- Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Journal letters, 1866 Sep 19- Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Journal letters, 1867 Feb 19- Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Journal letters, 1867 Jul 26- Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Journal letters, 1867 Nov 15- 1868 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Journal letters, 1868 Feb 17- Apr 20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Journal letters, 1868 May 5- Jul 13 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Journal letters, 1868 Jul 28- Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Journal letters, 1868 Oct 16- Dec 26 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Journal letters, 1869 Jan 7- Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Journal letters, 1869 May 7- Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Journal letters, 1869 Aug 11- Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Journal letters, 1869 Nov 1- Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Journal letters, 1870 Jan 1- Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Journal letters, 1870 Mar 7- May 30 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Journal letters, 1870 Jun 13- 1871 Mar 6 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Journal letters, 1871 Mar 6- Nov 10 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Journal letters, 1872 Jan 1- Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Mary Snell Smith letters to children
      - To Eunice, 1859 Jul 13- 1861 Jul 20 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - To Eunice, 1861 Sep 5- 1862 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - To Eunice, 1862 Feb 18- Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - To Eunice, 1862 Oct 3- 1865 Sep 9 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - To Eunice, 1865 Oct 14- Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - To Eunice, 1866 Jan 8- Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - To Eunice, 1866 Apr 9- Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - To Eunice, 1866 Sep 24- Dec 18 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - To Eunice, 1867 Jan 8- May 14 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - To Eunice, 1867 May 21- Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - To Eunice, 1867 Jul 9- Sep 23 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - To Eunice, 1867 Oct 10- Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - To Eunice, 1868 Jan 7- Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - To Eunice, 1868 Apr 1- May 21 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - To Eunice, 1868 Jun 5- Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - To Eunice, 1868 Sep 14- Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - To Eunice, 1869 Jan 4- Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - To Eunice, 1869 Mar 29- 1871 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - To Thomas, 1856 Jul 2, 1861 Oct 9 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - To Henry, 1859 Jul 13 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - To Mary E., 1859 Jul 13- 1867 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - To all describing sister Laura's death, 1872 Jun 7 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - John Curtis Smith
      - To Eunice, 1860 Dec 25- 1864 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      - To Eunice, 1864 May 23- 1867 Aug 19 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      - To Eunice, 1867 Dec 5- 1869 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      - To children, 1861 Apr 6- 1864 Feb 9 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      - To children, 1864 Feb 23- 1866 Jul 20 (Box 2, Folder 56)
      - To children, 1867 Feb 10- 1869 Jun 5 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - To children, 1869 Jun 18- 1870 Jun 8 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Thomas Snell Smith (Son)
      - To parents, 1868 Oct 11- Dec 16 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      - To parents, 1868 Dec 19- 1869 Jan 29 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      - To parents, 1869 Feb 5- Mar 8 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      - To parents, 1869 Mar 10- Apr 8 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - To parents, 1869 Apr 15- May 2 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      - To parents, 1869 May 3- May 19 (Box 2, Folder 64)
      - To parents, 1869 May 28- Jul 3 (Box 2, Folder 65)
      - To parents, 1869 Aug 9- Aug 23 (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - To sister Mary, 1861 May 25- Aug 27 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Eunice Morse Smith
      - To parents, 1859 Nov 2- 1868 Nov 21 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      - To parents, 1868 Nov 30- Dec 29 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      - To parents, 1869 Jan 4- Feb 15 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - To parents, 1869 Feb 26- Apr 6 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      - To parents, 1869 Apr 14- May 12 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      - To parents, 1869 May 20- Jun 21 (Box 2, Folder 73)
      - To parents, 1869 Jun 24- Aug 30 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      - To parents, 1868 Oct 15- Dec 19 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      - To parents, 1868 Dec 28- 1869 Feb 4 (Box 2, Folder 76)
      - To parents, 1869 Feb 15- Mar 22 (Box 2, Folder 77)
      - To parents, 1869 Mar 29- May 1 (Box 2, Folder 78)
      - To parents, 1869 May 7- May 31 (Box 2, Folder 79)
      - To parents, 1869 Jun 10- Aug 13 (Box 2, Folder 80)
      - Laura to sister Eunice, 1870 Nov 30 (Box 2, Folder 80a)
      - To dear ones: journal on board "Winged Hunter", 1870 Jan 28- Apr 25 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - William H. Smith
      - To parents, 1868 Jul 24- 1869 May 19 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Henry H. Smith
      - To parents, 1868 Oct 4- 1869 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Mary E. Smith
      - To parents, 1865 Mar 3- 1868 Dec 20 (Box 2, Folder 84)
      - To parents, 1869 Jan 1- Feb 15 (Box 2, Folder 85)
      - To parents, 1869 Feb 27- Mar 25 (Box 2, Folder 86)
      - To parents, 1869 Mar 30- Apr 28 (Box 2, Folder 87)
      - To parents, 1869 May 4- Jun 5 (Box 2, Folder 88)
      - To parents, 1869 Jun 12- Jul 10 (Box 2, Folder 89)
      - To parents, 1869 Jul 14- Aug 25 (Box 2, Folder 90)
      - To brother Thomas, 1865 Sep 29 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Extended family to MSS/JCS
      - From parents to MSS, 1837 Sep 27-1842 Oct 9 (Box 2, Folder 92)
      - From parents to MSS, 1843 Sep 31- 1848 Oct 21 (Box 2, Folder 93)
      - From parents to MSS, 1846 May 30- 1849 Aug 23 (Box 2, Folder 94)
      - From parents, sisters, niece to JCS, 1844 Oct 10- 1951 Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 95)
      - Asa Smith (brother) to JCS, 1841 Feb 7- 1843 Mar 29 (Box 2, Folder 96)
      - Asa Smith (brother) to JCS, 1843 Jul 26- 1843 Dec 4 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      - Asa Smith (brother) to JCS, 1844 Feb 5- 1844 Jun 29 (Box 2, Folder 98)
      - Asa Smith (brother) to JCS, 1844 Jul 31- 1844 Nov 26 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      - Asa Smith (brother) to JCS, 1844 Dec 14- 1845 Nov 24 (Box 2, Folder 100)
      - Asa Smith (brother) to JCS, 1846 Jun 9- 1846 May 26 (Box 2, Folder 101)
      - Asa and Sarah Smith to JCS and MSS, 1844 Dec 14- 1852 Jun 22 (Box 3, Folder 102)
      - Laura Smith Parkhurst (sister) to JCS and MSS, 1838 Mar 23- 1846 Mar 21 (Box 3, Folder 103)
      - Laura Smith Parkhurst (sister) to JCS and MSS, 1846 Jul 20- 1849 Mar 4 (Box 3, Folder 104)
      - Laura Smith Parkhurst (sister) to JCS and MSS, 1850 Jun 27- 1952 Jul 11 (Box 3, Folder 105)
      - Laura and Wm Parkhurst to JCS, 1842 Sep 24- 1846 Mar 24 (Box 3, Folder 106)
      - Marcia Smith Lynn (sister) to JCS, 1842 Sep 28- 1845 Apr 20 (Box 3, Folder 107)
      - Marcia Smith Lynn (sister) to JCS, 1845 Sep 8- 1847 Aug 31 (Box 3, Folder 108)
      - Marcia Smith Lynn (sister) to JCS, 1847 Oct 6- 1852 Aug 5 (Box 3, Folder 109)
      - James Lynn to JCS, 1851 Aug 11- 1855 Feb 10 (Box 3, Folder 110)
      - Lucia and Marcia (sisters) to JCS, 1842 Jun 7- 1843 Nov 12 (Box 3, Folder 111)
      - Lucia and Marcia (sisters) to JCS, 1844 May 20- 1847 Jan 28 (Box 3, Folder 112)
      - Lucia and Marcia (sisters) to JCS, 1847 Mar 10- 184? Aug 28 (Box 3, Folder 113)
      - Lucia and Marcia (sisters) to JCS, 1844 Apr 17- 1850 Feb 3 (Box 3, Folder 114)
      - Lucia and Marcia (sisters) to JCS, 1850 Jun 2- 1852 Mar 11 (Box 3, Folder 115)
      - Lucia Smith to JCS, 1842 Sep 10- 1845 Jun 21 (Box 3, Folder 116)
      - Lucia Smith to JCS, 1845 Aug 26- 1851 Mar 30 (Box 3, Folder 117)
      - Lucia Smith to JCS and MSS, 1845 Mar 23- 1849 Jul 8 (Box 3, Folder 118)
      - Laura, Lucia and Marcia to JCS and first wife, 1841 Jul 31- 1842 Jan 18 (Box 3, Folder 119)
      - Lucia and Marcia to MSS, 1845 Dec 19- 1849 Mar 28 (Box 3, Folder 120)
      - Eliza P. Hallock (sister) to MSS, 1861 Mar 29- 1863 Sep 19 (Box 3, Folder 121)
      - Martha S. Rood (niece) to MSS, 1863 Jun 10 (Box 3, Folder 122)
      - Harriet Smith (sister-in-law) to MSS, 1862 Feb 18 (Box 3, Folder 123)
      - Eben Snell (brother) to MSS, 1863 Dec 1 (Box 3, Folder 124)
      - Ebenezer Snell (cousin) and his dtr to MSS, 1847 Dec 29- 1866 Mar 1 (Box 3, Folder 125)
      - Phebe Snell Thorpe (cousin) to MSS, no date (Box 3, Folder 126)
    - Extended family to others
      - Laura S. Parkhurst to her mother Polly Waller Smith, 1843 Sep 6- 1851 Mar (Box 3, Folder 127)
      - Laura S. Parkhurst to her mother Polly Waller Smith, 1851 May- 1851 Jul 31 (Box 3, Folder 128)